hi my name is guy I'm the owner and
operator of your way CPR we teach CPR
first aid training for the healthcare
provider of non health care providers I
have been a medic for the past 26 years
been teaching CPR for the past 10 years
they choke an infant first of all is
there a way to find out if an infant is
choking well we put our hands to the
throat what do babies do basically their
eyes open up wide and their hands come
up you know they're in other words
they're saying somebody help me well we
have an instant right here that is going
to be choking here's what we do number
one we will grab their legs and lift up
the baby supporting their head putting
the baby in our hand supporting their
back our next step we take in our other
hand putting it right between the jaw to
avoid them closing their mouth and we're
going to be flipping them to the other
side our next step would be to sit down
and put the victim over your thigh in a
45 degree angle to help assist with
gravity the other hand will go right
between the shoulder blades and we're
going to pound five times our next step
would be to grab the infant flip them to
the other hand bringing them in to us
our middle finger between the nipples
the same location we do CPR and our
index below that 5 chest thrusts about 1
second each one we'll take a look inside
the victims mouth to see if we see
anything we do not and I repeat again we
do not put our fingers inside their
mouth to pull an item out unless we can
visually see it at the tip of the mouth
and then if we do not see anything we
will flip over and do it again until the
item comes out or god forbid until the
infant becomes unresponsive if they do
become unresponsive we will begin CPR
immediately