This demonstration should take about
five minutes
and be at a pace that you can follow
along to.
Before we start you should note your
tie has a skinny end and a fat end.
Your first decision is going to be which
side of your body you place the ends.
It doesn't matter which side your tie
goes on, it won't affect the tie tying process
I have posted a mirror image of
this video if that suits you better.
Not only does your tie have two ends,
it has two different sides:
the face side is smooth,
and the seam side
is on the back
We're going to start with the seam side
down so take your tie,
and with the seam side down, place it around your neck
flat against your body, again with the seam
side down.
Here's where we adjust for length. You pull
on the fat end so that the skinny end is
about at your rib cage. Now choosing length
is a very difficult step, it's a very
important step, but in this part of the
process we're just trying to tie
the tie properly, so we're going to skip it.
We will get to it later
now we're going to take the fat end and
cross it over the skinny end
move the skinny and over take the fat
end cross it over the skinny end,
making an "X".
You'll notice I have one hand
holding the bottom of the "X".
To simplify the process I'm going to
have one hand do all the work while the
other hand just holds
the center of the "X".
The center of the "X" becomes the knot
so I'm going to call the hand that holds
the "X", the "knot hand". Choose which hand
you want to be the "knot hand" and take
hold of the center of the "X".
make sure you have a good grip
and don't let go
but feel free to adjust later if you
need to.
Now the space between the center of the "X"
and your neck
is what i call the tie hole
it's this area here
now there's four places we can put the tie
we can make the tie come out of the hole
we can make the tie go into the hole
we can make the tie go behind the hole
and we can make the tie go across the hole
the first step we're going to do is take the
tie and make it go out of the hole
so take the tie
and make it go out of the hole
i do that by
placing my hand in the front of the tie
and then just push it straight up through the hole
with it half way through you can use your
knot hand to hold the bottom of the tie
as you move your working hand around
pull the rest of the tie through
flipping it over
and let it fall in front of you
now we're going to take the tie and make it go
behind the hole
so go ahead and grab the tie
pull it over to the side
and just push it straight through behind the hole
i'm going to place it on my shoulder so
you can see that the seam here
is now facing out
also take note
that this part here is kind of low
now w're going to take the tie
and make it go in to the hole
I'm going to grab under
flip it around and push it through the
hole
as I'm halfway through I'm going to grab it with my pinky, it's not necessary,
just go ahead and pull the rest of it through
again, now flipping it so the seam side
is showing
take a good look at the knot here feel
free to give a small tug on the tie
at the end of every step
you don't want it too tight, but then again not
too loose
we're not going to take the tie and go
across the hole
so take the tie, pull it over the side
and then make it go across the hole
at this point I have a good tip for you
before you go across the hole,
put your finger right here
again I'm going to place the tie on my
shoulder just so you can see
that the face is now showing
the next step is to take the tie and
make it go out of the hole again
as we do that we're going to kind of flip it
to take the time kind of just
push your fingers around and through
again as you make the tie go out of the hole
you're going to flip it over so again
the face is showing. In future it's at this
point you may want to switch hands
but then you won't have the benefit of
the tip i gave earlier
to finish your going to take the fat end
of the tie
and put it behind the across step
it's kind of hard to explain where that
is, which is why i told you to put your
finger there, so take the fat end
and make it go right where your finger is
again i'm using one hand here
but at this point it can be easier to
just grab the fat end with that one
finger either way you're going to pull
the fat end through and keep pulling
until the knot is tight as you're
pulling the knot tight make sure not to
lose the skinny end
you can squeeze the bottom to help form
the proper shape
pulling the two tops apart will also help
to tighten the tie around her neck grab
the skinny end with one hand and the
bottom of the knot with the other hand
and now you do a "pull and slide" motion
pull in the skinny end
slide the knot, pull, slide
tidy up a bit
make sure everything looks nice
and now you can flip your collar down
it's at this point you should also do up
the top button
give it one more tighten
and you're all done
now we just need to get the proper
length
and maybe a little faster