hello my name is chip and I'm a
paramedic with the state of North
Carolina today we're gonna talk a little
bit about how to identify and treat
someone that's choking for this purposes
we're gonna talk about an adult that's
choking the universal sign for choking
is typically this doesn't matter where
you are or who you are when you don't
get air going to your lungs anymore from
food or other kind of obstructions
you'll automatically when I grasp your
throat
another thing will not make any noise
when your airway is completely blocked
air cannot pass by and cannot allow your
vocal cords to do what they need to do
so you can speak and be audible so what
you want to do is you want to approach
the patient that has their hands up in
the choking symbol and you want to
identify yourself you know I'm here to
help you are you choking and believe it
or not they will oftentimes shake their
head yes or they won't be able to
respond at all and what you want to do
is have the person stand or help them
stand put your hands make a fist cover
your fist right around the belly button
area or just above the belt line and you
want to push in and up and rapid thrusts
in and up
you want to continue to do this until
the food is expelled or until they go
unconscious typically what you're doing
is when you're pushing in on the
abdominal area you're changing the the
force pressure so it's hopefully going
to push more pressure upward and allow
you only have two openings you have your
esophagus and you have your trachea once
to the lungs once to the belly I know
that you're gonna push and allow
whatever that obstruction in the airway
is to be forced out when that happens
I'm gonna make sure you have the
patients sit back down typically they'll
be coughing quite a bit when that
happens and so you want to make sure
they can breathe okay and if they vomit
they're leaning over so they don't
aspirate or suck any that back into
their lungs because that can cause a
problem if the patient's full-term
pregnant I'm gonna make sure you don't
push where the baby is
you go up higher around the breastbone
area and you put your hands here and you
do the thrust up here never wear the
full developed fetus is located on the
pregnant female this is chip and I hope
you've learned something about choking
thank you