I'm alone Stanley for howdini calm and
in this segment we'll be talking about
changing a flat tire
certainly it's inconvenient but we're
going to walk you through it step by
step lift up this cover to access the
spare tire well on loosen it go to hold
down then give it a couple good wrap
make sure it's full of air worst thing
you want to do is put on a flat spare
then you'll remove the tire careful this
can be quite heavy well we have our
spare tire in our Jack we've set our
reflective warning signal out
we've also dropped the wheel on the
opposite side of the flat tire so we're
ready to start changing it the first
thing we'll do is jack the vehicle up
you'll have to loosen the jack a little
bit in order to get the handle off this
particular model has the lug wrench
built right in before we Jack though
we'd want to loosen the lug nuts because
once it's jacked up it's going to be
very difficult to get those lug nuts off
this particular model has a hubcap
which will just loosen those up doesn't
take much because they're made out of
plastic set the hub cap out of the way
now you have access to the lug nuts
loosen the lug nuts position yourself
firmly pressing counterclockwise loosen
the lug nuts
not too loose just enough to crack them
this is a little stubborn position
yourself over using your knee or your
foot you can gain leverage now we're
ready to jack it up this is the common
scissors jack the screw moves in and out
allowing the mechanism to move up and
down and lift your car so as you turn it
to the right it'll go up as you loosen
it the jack will collapse allowing the
car to come down now we'll position the
jack you want to be sure to get the jack
on a good part of the frame your owner's
manuals a good place to find where to
properly jack the vehicle you can raise
it up by hand until it contacts the
frame it is in good position
we use the jack handle to raise the
vehicle insert the end of the jack
handle into the jack
using it as leverage it'll help make the
car go up easier remember to turn it
clockwise to go up and counterclockwise
to go down carefully Jack the car up
never stick your hands or your legs
under the vehicle as the car can fall
and cause damage checking can take a
while so be patient and cautious as you
jack
okay now that the car is jacked up now
we'll take the lug nuts loose remembered
we already pre loosened them when the
car was on the ground making it easy
you notice they'll come right off now
trying to do that while a car was jacked
up would be very difficult remember to
keep your lug nuts in closed hands you
don't want them rolling away in the
grass because it'll be hard to find and
that's what holds your tire on again
we're turning them counterclockwise to
get them loose or to the left we'll
remove the flat tire set it over here
out of the way
now if there was heavy traffic area you
wouldn't want to leave it in the street
you might want to put it to the rear of
the car grab the spare tire put it in
position you're going to Center the
spare tire on the wheel studs that's
where the lug nuts go so go ahead and do
that lining it up you see it lines up
pretty easy then install your lug nuts
again clockwise just tight
counterclockwise is loose so we'll
tighten them up by hand as far as
they'll go
once the tire centered lug nuts are hand
tight take the lug wrench again turning
it clockwise tighten the lugs till
they're firm not too tight because
remember your car is up on a jack we
wouldn't want it falling off with too
much leverage of force insert the jack
handle back into the jack turning it
counterclockwise again we're going to
lower the vehicle again this will take
some time but going downs a lot of user
than going up if he seems to be going
down easy you can just do it like this
by doing it straight instead of having
it angled but if it's too tough you can
angle it and get the leverage that
you'll need to lower the jack or to
raise the jack turn the jack lower
enough you can do it by hand now that it
doesn't have contact with the frame and
we can remove it now let the tires on
the ground we'll go ahead and give them
that final type and we're going to start
down here then move to the top one then
back down over and back again a little
star pattern making sure we have equal
torque on the wheel studs okay well we
have our spare tire on it's aired up
we're ready to go a couple things to
remember though is you want to put
everything back in the trunk you don't
want to exceed highway speed on this
temporary spare make sure you get the
big tire fixed and you'll get you back
on the road as soon as possible I'm Alan
Stanley for howdini dot-com
you