Hello, in this HealthSketch, we want to talk
to you about CPR,
which stands for Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation.
We use CPR when someone has collapsed and
is not breathing, because it can keep people
alive until emergency services arrive.
Learning these simple life-saving skills is
as easy as ABC - all you have to remember
is the “Doctor’s ABC”.
D is for Danger: First, look around carefully
to make sure the area is safe for yourself
and others before approaching.
R is for Response: Shake them gently by the
shoulders and ask them loudly “Are you alright?”
If there is no response, you need to...
S: Shout for help, as any assistance will
be helpful
A is for Airway: Gently tilt the head back
like this, to open up the airway.
B is for Breathing: Look, Listen and Feel
for signs of normal breathing: LOOK for normal
chest movements, LISTEN for normal breathing
sounds and try to FEEL their breath against
your face.
Do this for no more than 10 seconds.
If there is no sign of breathing, or if they
are breathing in an unusual, noisy way, we
need to start CPR.
First, make sure that an ambulance is on its
way.
If you have someone else with you, ask them
to make the call.
Putting the phone on speaker mode is useful
as the ambulance service can talk you through
the steps.
C is for Circulation: Circulation means the
flow of blood around the body, and when the
heart stops pumping, we need to take over
this role by pushing down hard and fast on
the chest.
Start by placing the heel of one hand at the
centre of the person’s chest and interlock
your fingers like this.
With arms straightened, press down hard and
fast, letting the chest come back up fully
each time.
Fast means around 2 times every second (metronome
sound) and hard means that the chest needs
to go down by about 5 centimetres.
This might sound a lot but you do need to
push hard for it to be effective.
If you have been trained, you can give 2 ‘rescue
breaths’ after every 30 compressions, as
this helps provide some oxygen.
However, if you have not been trained or are
not comfortable, just keep going with ‘Hands-only’
continuous chest compressions.
If someone else is with you, swap over if
you begin to feel tired, and don’t stop
until either a health professional takes over,
or the person is definitely breathing normally.
Sometimes, we can add another step – ‘D’.
D is for Defibrillation, which is about delivering
a shock to restart the heartbeat.
Some public areas and workplaces have an easy-to-use
defibrillator on site, called an Automatic
External Defibrillator, or AED.
Automatic means that it is the machine that
decides what to do, so you can’t go wrong,
and it even talks you through the steps.
If there is no AED available, keep going with
CPR until the ambulance arrives.
That’s it!
So to recap: remember DR’S ABC and if you
have it, D. That’s D for Danger, R for response.
S for shout for help, A for Airway, B for
Breathing, C for Circulation and D for Defibrillation.
In this HealthSketch, we’ve shown you the
simple steps you can take to help someone
who has collapsed, is not breathing, or not
breathing normally.
Why not take a training course to practice
these steps.
Share this video with friends and family to
make sure we all know what to do.