One, two three four!
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Rev up your engines!
[REVVING ENGINE]
[SCREECHING TIRES]
[SKIDS TO STOP]
It's time for Scottykilmer.com.
OK.
It's happened to all of us.
You get in your car and turn the
key and the only thing you hear
is a click.
So what do you do?
You open the hood and check.
Up it goes.
Now, if your battery
is weak, the starter
will click because it
doesn't have enough juice
to turn the engine over.
So try jump-starting it first.
Get good battery cables.
Cheap ones will melt
or won't work right.
Put the positive on the
positive of your donor battery
and put the other positive
end on the positive
of the battery in your car.
Then put one of the negative
cables on the negative terminal
of your donor battery.
Clamp the other negative
one on any solid metal
part on the engine.
That keeps the battery from
accidentally blowing up
from hydrogen vapor.
Now, we'll turn it.
And nope, the car
still won't start.
So I know the battery is good.
It's not the battery.
Now, generally, either
the starter's bad
or the engine is locked up.
So let's try turning
the engine by hand
to see if it's locked up.
We'll take the wheel
out of the way.
And there's the current
shaft fold right here.
You will get a cheater bar and
a socket that fits on there.
We'll put it on the bolt and
see if we can turn the engine.
Now, it turns so we know
the engine isn't locked up.
That leaves the number one
culprit being a bad starter.
So let's take the
starter off and test it.
Now, in this car,
the starter is easier
to access from the bottom,
so you jack it up in the air
and there's the starter
motor right there.
We can test it by
hot-wiring it first to see
if it'll work if we do that.
Now, in this starter motor,
this little wire here
is the one that energizes it,
so we'll put a jumper wire
on top of that little wire.
Touch it on the positive
terminal of the battery.
Well, it's a good thing we
did that because there's
nothing wrong with the starter.
There's a problem in the wiring
system that we have to fix.
Now, starting systems
have relays and switches
and all kinds of things in them.
But I noticed the backup
lights are on in this car.
Now the backup lights
stay on in this car,
whether it's in park, neutral,
drive-- it doesn't matter.
So there's got to be a problem
in the transmission range
sensors.
It's probably broken.
So I called up a Chevy
dealer and they're $163.
And considering the
shape of this old car
with a taped-on mirror
that just fell off
and body parts that are
barely even hanging on,
I'm just going to bypass it.
Splice the two wires together
to bypass the switch so
that it'll start all the time.
The owner doesn't care.
He just wants the car
to start and as long
as he remembers if
it's in drive and he
hits the start and
the car will start,
it's not going to hurt anything.
You just go down to
the neutral safety
switch here and pull
the connector off.
Here's the connector.
Then with the test
light, see which one gets
power when you turn the key on.
And in this case,
it's this wire.
Then find the wire that
when it gets power,
turns the starter on like this.
You get power with
your device and then
the engine starts right up.
Then you just splice those two
wires together and it'll start.
Now, granted, it'll
start in all gears now.
But it saved a
whole bunch of money
and this old thing, who
knows how much longer it's
going to be on the road anyway.
So the next time your
car doesn't do anything
when you turn the key
and try to start it,
why not fix it yourself.
And remember, if you
have any car questions,
just visit the
Scottykilmerchannel.
[MUSIC PLAYING]