hey guys and welcome back to crouton
crackerjacks today I'm gonna show you
how to make easy and delicious french
toast
you know french toast is one of those
things doesn't need to be complicated it
doesn't need any fancy ingredients you
know sometimes it's better just to keep
things as simple and french toast is one
of those things so without further ado
let's get this recipe started alright
first thing obviously I'm going to need
a batter for my bread so what a pie
plate here I'm just gonna crack in two
large eggs and do better than I did and
try not to get shells in your eggs
no one likes crunchy bits in that french
toast I'm just gonna crack those two
eggs into a pie plate and using a fork
I'm just gonna break these up a little
bit before I add the rest ingredients
the reason I'm using a pie plate here is
for when I go to coat my bread it's just
easier to do it on a wide shallow bowl
to my eggs I'm going to add in a quarter
of a cup of milk you could also use
cream or half-and-half if you're feeling
it decadent I'm going to add in one
teaspoon of granulated sugar as well as
1/8 of a teaspoon or 1/4 teaspoon of
cinnamon just a pinch of salt maybe an
eighth of a teaspoon or so and just a
quick splash of vanilla trying to use
real vanilla extract though and using a
fork I'm just gonna whisk these
ingredients together just make sure that
all the eggs are completely smooth the
milk kind of helps break up those eggs
you don't want to need globules of egg
on your french toast you want to smooth
batter so I just whisk that well and let
me just talk about bread for a minute
here I am using Texas toast Texas toast
is just regular sandwich bread but it is
actually kit cut thicker than a regular
sandwich bread it's kind of a dry bread
crummy bread and these particular slices
are about three quarters of an inch
thick and that's exactly what you want
you want a thick bread for this and I'm
just using this regular sandwich bread
you could use brioche if you wanted to
or French bread you know whatever kind
of bread that you like I just happen to
like just plain old sandwich bread it
just it makes the best french toast to
me now I've got a frying pan over
medium-high heat here it's actually
between median and medium-high I'm going
to add in about a teaspoon of vegetable
oil as well as just a little
pat of butter now the reason I add both
vegetable oil and butter is because I
like the flavor of frying and butter as
well butter kind of has a natural
nonstick property to it but the
vegetable oil raises the burning point
of the butters the butter doesn't burn
because you definitely don't want burn
butter on your french toast well maybe
you do but I don't so that's why I do
both and you want to make sure that your
butter and oil are hot before you add in
your first piece of French toast
otherwise your french toast is gonna
stick and you don't want it to stick and
you know when it's ready when the solids
the milk solids in the butter start to
brown I don't know how well you can see
this in the video but they're just
starting to turn golden that is the
exact time that your pan is ready for
your french toast so what I'm gonna do
is just kind of mix up my french toast
my batter mixture a little bit here make
sure that the cinnamon isn't you know
sticking to the bottom and duck your
bread just really quickly on one side
flip it over get it coated on the other
side let it drip a little bit and then
add that to your pan now a lot of
recipes for French toast call for you to
soak the bread I do not like soaked
bread for French toast maybe you do I
don't I like my french toast to not be
custardy I like it to still be bread in
the center so I just do a light coat on
both sides and I'm just gonna let this
go for a couple minutes until it gets
nice and golden brown on the bottom
don't be tempted to move your bread
around you know just let the pan do its
work but the heat do its work you know
when you're getting ready to flip when
the bubbles around the outside get a
little smaller and they don't pop so
aggressively so go ahead and take a peek
make sure that it is nice and golden
brown and then you can go ahead and flip
it over and cook it on the other side
again just cook it for a minute or two
just until those bubbles around the
outside kind of simmer down and then you
can go ahead and remove that off to the
plate add just a little bit more butter
and vegetable oil to your pan between
each slice and continue frying up the
rest of your french toast and this
mixture using two eggs will do for me
personally six pieces of
X's toast which is just perfect for me
and my roommate so yeah just go ahead
and keep french toasting all of your
bread pieces and then you can go ahead
and or some delicious maple syrup right
over top if you're feeling extra
decadent that's the top with a little
bit of powdered sugar if you'd like you
can serve these with fried eggs and
bacon on the side or if you want just
like a little bowl of fresh fruit would
be delicious but yeah like I said
sometimes it's better just to keep
things simple and french toast is one of
those things so go ahead and give this
recipe a try if you do and you like it
go ahead and let me know down below in
the comments if you liked this video be
sure to give a thumbs up subscribe for
more deliciousness and keep up to date
on all my latest videos thanks so much
for watching and we will see you next
time