This recipe makes the softest fluffiest pancakes
and most if not all of the ingredients you
should be able to find in your kitchen.
Pour yourself a cup of coffee and whip these
up for brunch this weekend.
Start by measuring out a cup and half of all
purpose flour into a large mixing bowl.
This recipe makes enough for 3-4 people so
if you are cooking for more just double the
recipe.
You can find a printable version on my website,
or check the information box below for the
measurements.
In the same bowl as the flour measure out
4 teaspoons of baking powder.
4 may seem like a lot, but this is the secret
to getting the softest, fluffiest pancakes.
As the pancakes cook the baking powder is
going to react and create an abundance of
air, getting that perfect pancake texture.
Lastly to the dry ingredients add a pinch
of salt.
You can add sugar here as well if you would
like, around a tablespoon, but I prefer to
add sweetness with toppings rather than with
the actual pancake.
Use a wooden spoon to mix the dry ingredients
together until they are combined.
Set the bowl to the side.
In a smaller bowl to mix together the wet
ingredients.
First crack in on large free range egg, followed
by the milk.
I’m using dairy but you can substitute with
soy or almond if you would like.
To the egg and milk add in a 1/4 cup of cooled
melted butter.
Use a fork to mix everything together, making
sure the egg is well incorporated.
This is optional, but I love a hint of vanilla.
Add half a teaspoon of pure vanilla essence
and mix again.
Make a well in flour and pour in the wet ingredients.
Fold the batter together with a wooden spoon
until there are no longer any large lumps..
Make sure you’re not over mixing as this
will lead to your pancakes being quite tough.
I’ve kept these pancakes quite pain but
if you do want to add blueberries or chocolate
chips, or any other flavourings now would
be a good time.
When you are ready to cook the pancakes heat
a heavy bottomed pan like cast iron over medium
low heat.
When the pan has heated add a small amount
of butter to the pan to melt.
Scoop out about a 1/3 of a cup of batter and
pour into the pan.
Leave the pancake to spread on it’s own
and cook for a few minutes.
You’ll know it’s ready to flip when air
bubbles start to form on the top.
If you are unsure just use a spatula to lift
up the side and check the bottom.
Flip and cook for a further few minutes on
the opposite side.
If your pancakes are browning a little to
quickly just adjust the heat.
Place the cooked pancake on a plate and repeat
with the next.
You should get about 6 or 7 pancakes out of
this recipe so continue until you are out
of batter.
Top the pancakes with maple syrup and any
of your other favourite toppings.
Send me a photo if you try out this recipe,
I would love to see your favourite pancake
topping.
Thank you for watching, I hope you enjoyed
this recipe and I will see you in my next
video.
Bye.