[Music]
now we're gonna talk about the proper
way to hold the guitar as you can see
the guitar has an arch right here this
fits pretty perfectly over your thigh so
for guys you can hold it like this this
would be maybe more appropriate for for
a woman that battle fit and sit pretty
comfortably right over your thigh now
your right hand you want your forearm
right here resting comfortably on the
body of the guitar about right here in
this area you want the palm of your hand
this this part right here to rest
lightly on the bridge not in front to
where you're muting the strings right
behind right behind there that gives you
get pivot point it'll give your right
hand a lot more control you definitely
don't want to be floating around out
here at least for the exercises we're
gonna be doing in the beginning here say
you wanna pivot that plant that so you
can pivot right there
on the bridge of the guitar now your
left hand you want your thumb on the
back of the neck like that not the pad
you want the pad of your thumb not the
tip you don't want to hold it like this
you want to hold it like that then you
want to wrap your hands around so that
when you're pressing down on the on the
fret that your fingers are arched like
that so you always want to be playing
with the tips of your fingers not the
pads of your fingers you always want to
try to be on your tips your fingers
gonna get really sore at first but that
will go away if you over time as you
practice you want to wrap it around and
arch your fingers like this you always
want to be able to have a gap between
your poem here and the bottom of the
neck you don't want to be resting your
palm up against the bottom of the neck
so always one that you should always be
able really like fit a pencil between
or something okay now we're going to go
back to our right hand so we got our
palm lightly on the bridge for a pivot
point you're gonna hold your pick with
either your thumb and two fingers or
your thumb and your first finger either
way is acceptable you did not want to
hold the pick like this it's kind of a
bad habit to start so that that would be
the proper way to hold it or like that
so with our right hand resting on the
bridge I just want you to pick the sixth
string that's your E string and just
pick one time down now we do something
on guitar called alternating your
picking you do downstrokes and upstrokes
so going down toward the floor would be
a Down stroke picking up B an upstroke
so I just want you to hit the sixth
string the E string that's also referred
to as the low E string I want you to hit
that four times
alternating you're picking up and down
so
now I want to go down to the fifth
string that's your a string don't you
pick that four times alternating you're
picking
[Music]
now we're going to go to the fourth
string that's your D string pick that
four times
now to our third string which is G pick
that four times remember to keep your
palm rested on the bridge pick our
second string that's B pick that four
times
and finally our first string which is e
or often referred to as the high E
string pick that four times just make
sure that before you move on you have
that alternating picking method down
[Music]
it's also really important to memorize
the notes of the open strings when I say
open strings I mean the note that you're
playing without putting any fingers down
with your left hand so when I pick this
string the sixth string that is a low E
or an e note the fifth string is a
fourth string is d the third string is G
second string is B and the first string
is e or high E it's important to
memorize those notes for now I wouldn't
worry about any of memorizing any other
notes on the fretboard except for the
open strings for now now we're gonna
finish up the lesson and I'm gonna show
you a simple exercise incorporating our
left and right hand this is just a
simple exercise to work on you or your
muscle-memory your finger dexterity your
coordination between your left and right
hands so with your left hand now thumb
on the back of the neck arched fingers
playing with your fingertip with your
first finger
that would be your index finger on the
fifth fret now when you fret you want to
be right behind the actual fret the
silver piece you want to be right behind
it as close as close to it as you
possibly can without being on top of it
that'll give you the best tone the best
sound if you're back here a lot of times
you get kind of a bad buzzing sound so
you want to be right up against that
fret that'll give you a nice clear tone
so now with your right hand technique
palm on the bridge I want you to press
down you've got to press down pretty
hard I want you to pick that four times
alternating your picking
[Music]
now with your second finger once you go
one fret up on the sixth fret leaving
your first finger down pick that four
times then with your third finger your
ring finger go the next fret up that's
the seventh fret still leaving all your
fingers down pick that four times
finally your pinky or your fourth finger
on the eighth fret
[Applause]
[Music]
remember the whole time to be
alternating you're picking up and down
strokes now we're gonna go to the a
string and do the exact same thing
starting with our first finger four
times second finger third finger
[Music]
fourth finger then we're gonna go the
fourth string D string same thing again
this is just an exercise to get your
fingers moving and build up the
coordination between your left and right
hand I'm just gonna work all the way
down all the strings when you get to
there I want you to go backwards
[Music]
all the way down so you get back to
where you started now go as slow as you
need to go if it's that's fine it's
better to be slow and precise and fast
and sloppy you can always work up to
faster now once you get it down where
you playing each note twice anyway then
I want you to just play each note one
time you're still palm on the bridge
you're still alternating you're picking
you know what you're really working for
a tour bird is something that sounds
like this once you get it down slow then
you can boat work on your speed
[Music]
I want you to practice this all over the
next so you can start on the first fret
[Music]
then go to the second fret third fret
and so on all the way down I want you to
make sure that your notes are even
evenly spaced out so so you want to
avoid being like you want to make sure
they're all even what you especially
want to work on is going from one string
to the next so when you go from the
pinkie to your first finger back down
here the the a string
[Music]
so you want to make sure you got smooth
transitions going from each string so
once you get that down then you'll be
ready for lesson two but I would
strongly encourage you to not move on
until you can play that pretty smoothly
without thinking about it too much
you