- Hey everyone, my name
is Jacques Hopkins,
and thank you so much for
joining me here today,
where we're going to learn some piano.
In this lesson, I'm going to take you
from the very, very beginning
of the piano learning process,
all the way to, at the end of this lesson,
you're going to be able to
play a song on the piano.
And not just any song, it's
not gonna be Three Blind Mice
or something like that.
We're gonna play a
very, very popular song.
We're gonna play "Let It Be",
by the one and only, The Beatles.
In just about 15 minutes
or so, in this lesson.
I will take you from,
even if you've never
touched a piano before,
to being able to play "Let
It Be", by The Beatles.
So let's go ahead and get started.
Now, this is my keyboard, it has 88 keys.
That is a standard amount
of keys for any piano.
If you have a keyboard,
that has less than 88 keys,
chances are that's okay.
I want you to have at least 49 keys.
So if you have at least 49 keys,
then you're ready to get started.
If you don't have 49 keys,
if you have less than that,
you can give this a shot,
but keep in mind that I did warn you,
you may not have enough
room for both of your hands.
Now, if you're not
familiar with the piano,
if you don't know how to play it,
just looking at one could be intimidating.
Alright, so we have 88 keys here.
There's these black keys,
there's these white keys.
You know, what's the
difference between the two?
And that's the first step,
is we're gonna learn what
all the notes are called
on the piano, so you can play all them,
each individual note.
Alright, so, you don't have to memorize
all 88 keys on the piano.
You just have to memorize these sections
of 12 keys, because those
patterns, those sections,
they just repeat themselves
over and over again,
across the entire piano.
So let's zoom in on one of
these sections of 12 keys.
You'll notice there are seven white keys,
and there are five black keys.
You see these two black
keys that are together,
and then we have these three
black keys are together.
Look at that pattern, that
pattern just repeats itself
across the entire piano.
So, there's not really 88
different notes on the piano.
There's really 12 different notes.
So we need to learn these 12 notes,
and once you've learned those 12 notes,
you've learned all 88 of them.
So, let's dive right in.
The most popular note,
you probably have heard it before, it's C.
Alright, right here is
C, it's the white note
just to the left of the
any two black notes.
So this is C, this is
C, this is C and so on.
But we're just gonna focus in
on this section right here.
So, in music, we go to the right,
we go continue down the alphabet.
So we go C, D, E,
F, G, and then in music,
not just piano, but in music,
the letters start over after G.
So after G is not H,
there's no H in music.
This is A, and then B.
So again, C, D, E, F, G, A, and B.
So there's the seven white notes.
And then we have the five black notes.
So these black notes are
named for their relationship
with the white note next to them, okay.
So, for example, right here,
this is called C sharp,
and it's also D flat.
So every black note does
have two names, okay.
But the way you remember
which one is which,
like which way is sharp,
which way is flat,
is like this.
Sharp, the word sharp has five
letters in the word, right?
So does the word right.
So sharp and right always go together.
Flat and left both have
four letters in the word,
so a flat is always to the left
of the corresponding white note.
So that's why this is D
flat, and also C sharp.
So let's keep going down
and learn the other five black notes.
This is D sharp, and it's also E flat.
Alright, so what's this one right here?
We have F sharp, and it's also G flat.
This one is G sharp, and it's also A flat.
And finally we have
this one, it's A sharp,
it's also B flat.
Okay, so there's 12 notes.
One of the first steps to
learning how to play piano
is just learning those keys.
And the best way to do that
is just with some flashcards,
or you can just get somebody,
a friend or family member,
to randomly call one out for you,
and you need to go,
and you need to play it
as quickly as you possibly can.
And you just drill that
until these 12 notes
become second nature for you.
Now, what I don't wanna
see from you at this point
is you learn C, you figure out where C is,
and you just think you
know all the other keys,
just because you know C.
So if I say play me a G key,
I don't want you going
okay, here's C, D, E, F, G.
Okay I got it.
No, I want, I want to say G,
and you go boom, right to G.
I like to think of it
like the days of the week.
If I ask you to tell me about Wednesday,
you're not gonna start
counting at Sunday or Monday,
and count, okay, Sunday,
Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday,
okay it's the fourth day of the week.
No, you're not gonna do that,
that would just be silly.
You already know, it's
second nature for you,
you know that Wednesday's
the middle weekday,
it comes after Tuesday,
it comes before Thursday.
Had to think about it for a second.
So, I want you to get to a point
with these notes on the piano.
There's no reason you can't
know the notes on the piano,
just as well as you know
the days of the week.
So before you move too
far ahead with the piano,
you're going to set yourself up
with such a great foundation,
if you truly learn just these 12 notes.
Okay, so once you do
that, the next step is,
we're gonna start playing
chords on the piano.
What a chord is is simply multiple notes
played at the same time.
Whereas, we were just
playing single notes,
this is a C note, this is not a chord.
This right here would be a chord,
because it's multiple notes
played at the same time.
And chords, when you put chords together,
that's actually how we build
modern songs on the piano.
And the majority of songs use chords
that fall into one of two categories.
We have the major chords, and
the we have the minor chords.
Okay, so the major chords are the ones,
they sound a little
more happy and cheerful.
Kind of like this, this is a major chord.
(strikes major chord on keyboard)
And then the minor chords,
they're a little more sad and dreary.
So this is an example of a minor chord.
(strikes minor chord on keyboard)
So can you hear the difference there?
Major chord.
(strikes major chord on keyboard)
Minor chord.
(strikes minor chord on keyboard)
And most modern songs will have a good mix
of major chords and minor chords.
Now, there's a lot of them,
but you don't have to
memorize each and every one.
That's the beauty of patterns and formulas
and piano, it's really
not a hard instrument.
So I'm gonna share with
you a very simple formula
for major chords, and once
you know this formula,
you know all the major chords.
And I'll share with you the
formula for minor chords,
and once you learn that formula,
you know all the minor chords.
It's a very simple formula.
So for major chords, that
formula is simply four, three.
Here's how you use that.
Let's say we wanna play a G major chord.
Okay, so we'll start at G,
we'll go to the right,
the very next four notes,
and it doesn't matter black or white,
whatever's next, count it.
So one, two, three, four.
There's four, and then we'll go three.
One, two, three.
There's a G major chord.
Go ahead and play with your thumb,
your middle finger, and
your pinky finger for now.
G major.
Let's try one more major chord.
Let's do a D major chord.
So we'll start at D.
One, two, three, four.
One, two, three.
D major.
Even if you ran into
something super complicated
like a B flat major chord,
don't get overwhelmed.
Just use the formula.
It's still just four, three.
B flat, left because it's flat.
One, two, three, four.
One, two, three.
B flat major chord.
Alright, let's do minor chords.
The formula for minor
chords is very, very similar
to the formula for major chords,
you just to reverse it.
So it's three and then four.
So let's say we wanted to play E minor.
We start at E, we go one, two, three.
And then one, two, three, four.
E minor.
Let's try C minor.
C, one, two, three.
One, two, three, four.
Okay.
So one thing I wanna point out here
is the difference between
a major and a minor chord.
If you look at the notes you play,
it's actually only one note difference,
and that's because four
plus three is seven
and also three plus four is seven.
So let's take the C chord as an example.
Here we have a C major chord.
The only difference between
a major and a minor chord
is the middle note.
(striking minor and
major chords alternately)
There we go.
So you're going to want
to practice your chords.
Practice your major chords,
practice your minor chords,
and then we can start playing
our favorite songs on the piano
because they're just built
with mostly major and minor chords.
Now that we've got the major
and minor chords nailed down,
I want you to go ahead
and let's learn how to
play the left hand as well.
And at this point, I want to
see if your hand is big enough
to do what I'd like you to do,
and if not, I've got a
different method for you.
But what we're going to
do is we're going to play
a C major chord.
In our left hand, I just
want you to play two C's,
one with your pinky and
one with your thumb.
(strikes C major chord on keyboard)
So like that, that's how we're
going to play a C major chord
and the left hand is the same
whether it's major or minor.
So a C minor would be like this.
If you cannot reach
your fingers like that,
if you have small hands
and that's just not comfortable for you,
what I want you to do is just
play one note instead of two,
so like this:
(strikes major chord)
or like this:
(strikes minor chord)
No problem.
Alright, so now that we
know how to play both hands,
major and minor chords, let's
go ahead and work on the song
that I told you about,
"Let it Be" by The Beatles.
The way this goes is we're going to start
with a C major chord
and you play it twice.
(strikes chord twice on keyboard)
And then it goes to G
major, play that twice.
(strikes chord twice on keyboard)
And then we have A minor.
And then we have F major.
(strikes chord twice on keyboard)
Okay?
And then we go back to C major.
(strikes chord twice on keyboard)
And then G major.
So everything so far,
all the chords I mentioned so far,
there's been six of
them, we play them twice.
Now there's four more chords
and you just play them once
and one of them is a little tricky.
It's gonna be the trickiest
part of this whole song,
but I'm gonna hold your
hand right through it.
So we have four more chords,
and you're just going
to play them one time.
So we have F major.
Alright, this next one is the tricky one.
We're going to do what's called a C/E,
and what that means is
we're going to do a C
on our right hand while
doing an E in our left hand.
Okay, and then the last
two are pretty standard,
we go to a D minor and then a C major.
Right, so let me hit
those last four again.
It's F, then it's C/E, D minor, C.
Alright, so let's run through
that whole sequence again.
Remember the first six chords we do,
you play them twice
and then the last four,
you just play them once.
(striking chords on keyboard)
You see how that's starting to sound like
"Let it Be" by The Beatles?
Let me do it for you just one more time
and then go ahead and practice
these chords on your own.
It's 10 chords in all.
Remember the first six,
we're gonna play them twice,
and the last four, we're
going to do it once.
(striking chords on keyboard)
So now you'll hopefully be able to impress
all your friends and family
by being able to play "Let
It Be" by The Beatles,
at least a basic version of that song.
If you're ready to learn
the more advanced techniques
with that song and countless others,
if you're ready to learn how
to learn new songs on your own,
head over to my website
at pianoin21days.com.
I've got a free resource,
more free lessons for you waiting there.
I've got the first five
days worth of lessons
waiting for you and a free workbook.
Again, just head to pianoin21days.com
or just click the link in the
description below this video.