removing and replacing the rear wheel on
your road bike can seem quite tricky but
fortunately it is a simple skill to
master when you know how to do it so
there's no reason why you can't do it or
in fact why you need to spend an
embarassing few minutes in a car park in
front of an ever-increasing audience
trying desperately to get it back in
there's a technique to it so here's how
to do it firstly you need to change into
your hardest gear so the smallest cog at
the back and that means that the rear
wheel will come out much easier as the
chain won't get caught on it when it's
coming out then you may well have to
open the brakes out slightly
to allow more room for the tyre to pass
between the brake pads so to do that
you're likely to have a little lever on
the side of the caliper just down here
now you either give it a twist or you
lift it depending on which manufacturers
brakes you've got and you'll see that
there's just a little bit more clearance
between the pads and the wheel so then
with your chain in the smallest cog at
the back and your brakes open open the
quick-release there's easy to unwind
it's off your back wheel there'll be
enough room now for the wheel to just
drop out next hold on to the top tube
here and then with your other hand reach
down and just pull the rear derailleur
backwards ever so slightly and then lift
up with your hands and you'll see the
back wheel just drops straight out and
with your other hand grab hold of the
back wheel and just unhook the chain
there you go back wheels off
let's replace it simply reverse the
procedure put your back wheel on the
floor and then using your hand that's on
the frame just guide the lower loop of
chain underneath the sprockets and then
just rest the derailleur on that
smallest sprocket and then push the
derailleur back again with that other
hand and the back wheel will just drop
in now if it doesn't go in straight away
you might just need to give it a little
nudge so just take all of the
quick-release maybe just tweak it
sideways slightly that's all it will
need now just make sure that the back
wheel is in squarely you can tell by
looking between the brake calipers to
make sure there's the same amount of
room on either side but also crucially
there little bit of frame down here so
you can see very easily whether it seems
straight when it is then you close the
quick-release lever now it should be at
the right tension because you haven't
moved it remember but to double check
you shouldn't ever have to really force
the quick-release shut it should be firm
but not too tight if it is too tight and
potentially is the risk that the
quick-release will actually break but it
is unlikely finally then it just close
your rear brakes up and give the back
wheel to spin just to make sure that it
is definitely not rubbing and there you
go a very very simple process when you
know how now if you want to see exactly
what to do with your back wheel off such
as maybe fixing a puncture then you can
get through to a video just by clicking
up there but for another common
complaint if your gears is jumping
around and they're just not quite
working properly then we've got a video
about how to index them you can get
through to that by clicking down there
otherwise just click on the subscribe to
GCN to make sure you don't miss any
other mechanical videos
[Applause]